{"BOOK/?lang=eng":{"booklist":[{"title":"Romans 2017-2018","lessons":[{"id":"2017_1","name":"Lesson1 Romans1:1-17 (09/18)"},{"id":"2017_2","name":"Lesson2 Romans1:18-32 (09/25)"},{"id":"2017_3","name":"Lesson3 Romans2 (10/02)"},{"id":"2017_4","name":"Lesson4 Romans3:1-20 (10/09)"},{"id":"2017_5","name":"Lesson5 Romans3:21-26 (10/16)"},{"id":"2017_6","name":"Lesson6 Romans3:27-31 (10/23)"},{"id":"2017_7","name":"Lesson7 Romans4 (10/30)"},{"id":"2017_8","name":"Lesson8 Romans5:1-11 (11/06)"},{"id":"2017_9","name":"Lesson9 Romans5:12-21 (11/13)"},{"id":"2017_10","name":"Lesson10 Romans6:1-11 (11/20)"},{"id":"2017_11","name":"Lesson11 Romans6:12-23 (11/27)"},{"id":"2017_12","name":"Lesson12 Romans7 (12/04)"},{"id":"2017_13","name":"Lesson13 Romans8:1-17 (12/11)"},{"id":"2017_14","name":"Lesson14 Romans8:18-27 (01/08)"},{"id":"2017_15","name":"Lesson15 Romans8:28-39 (01/15)"},{"id":"2017_16","name":"Lesson16 Romans9:1-29 (01/22)"},{"id":"2017_17","name":"Lesson17 Romans9:30-10:13 (01/29)"}]}]},"LESSON/2017_1?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_1","name":"Romans2017_1","memoryVerse":"“For I am not ashamed of the gospel, because it is the power of God that brings salvation to everyone who believes: first to the Jew, then to the Gentile.” – Romans 1:16 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_1_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 1:1-7.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:1-7"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_3","questionText":"3. What do you learn about Paul from his introduction? (See also Acts 9:1-21; 1 Timothy 1:12-16.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"9:1-21"},{"book":"1 Timothy","verse":"1:12-16"}]},{"id":"2017_1_4","questionText":"4. The word “gospel” means “good news.” What news do these verses announce, why is it good, and how have you experienced this goodness? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_5","questionText":"5. How did Paul describe the Roman Christians, what did he offer them, and how do his words affect your attitude about yourself or other believers? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 1:8-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:8-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_6","questionText":"6. Whom did Paul thank, and why was he grateful?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_7","questionText":"7. What do you learn about the relationship between serving God and prayer? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_8a","questionText":"8. a.  For what specifically did Paul pray, and how did God answer Paul’s prayer? (See Acts 28:14-20,30-31.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"28:14-20"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"28:30-31"}]},{"id":"2017_1_8b","questionText":"8. b. What do you learn about God from Paul’s prayers, and for whom or for what does this encourage you to pray?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 1:11-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:11-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_9","questionText":"9. Why did Paul want to come to the Roman church, and why had he not come previously?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_10","questionText":"10.  How could Paul’s example help you when you face obstacles in serving God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_11","questionText":"11. Why was Paul obligated to all people, and what was his attitude toward his obligation? What is your attitude toward your obligation to share your knowledge of Jesus with others? (See also Acts 26:11-18.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"26:11-18"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 1:16-17. Note: These verses are the theme of the entire book of Romans.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:16-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_12","questionText":"12. List reasons Paul was not ashamed of the gospel. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_13","questionText":"13. In what situations are you tempted to be ashamed of the gospel, and how could Paul’s reasons help you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_1_14","questionText":"14. How do these verses relate to your personal experience of the gospel, and how are they also Paul’s personal  testimony? (See Philippians 3:4-9.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:4-9"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 1:1-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_1_15","questionText":"15.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_2?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_2","name":"Romans2017_2","memoryVerse":"“For in the gospel the righteousness of God is revealed – a righteousness that is by faith from first to last, just as it is written: ‘The righteous will live by faith.’ ” – Romans 1:17 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_2_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 1:18-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:18-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_3","questionText":"3.  Define the word “wrath,” and explain from these verses why God is revealing His wrath at the present time. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_4a","questionText":"4. a.  What can we learn about God from the natural world, and how can this encourage your own personal worship and conversations with unbelievers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_4b","questionText":"4. b.  What can we not learn about God from nature, and how may we learn these necessary truths?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_5","questionText":"5.  Define the word “suppress.” What results of suppressing the truth do you see in your own life and what will you ask God to help you do about it? How might that impact others who suppress the truth?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 1:21-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:21-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_6","questionText":"6.  From these verses, how has humanity rejected the knowledge of God that His creation reveals?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_7a","questionText":"7. a.  What is the first result of rejecting God, and why is this consequence appropriate?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_7b","questionText":"7. b.  What has God done about light in a dark world, and how can you bring God’s light to those around you who live in darkness? (See also John 1:4-9; 8:12; Matthew 5:14-16.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"1:4-9"},{"book":"John","verse":"8:12"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"5:14-16"}]},{"id":"2017_2_8","questionText":"8.  In verses 22-23, what exchange has humanity made, and how do these verses, as well as today’s world, show this exchange leads to degrading practices? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 1:24-28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:24-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_9a","questionText":"9. a.  What truth about God do these verses indicate humanity has exchanged for a lie?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_9b","questionText":"9. b.  What substitutes for God could you be worshipping or serving, and how would your life be impacted if God removed those substitutes?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_10","questionText":"10.  What are some of the reasons God links the sin of idolatry to sexual immorality? (See Genesis 1:26-27; 2:24-25; Mark 10:8-9; 1 Corinthians 6:9-11, 18-20.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"1:26-27"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"2:24-25"},{"book":"Mark","verse":"10:8-9"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"6:9-11"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"6:18-20"}]},{"id":"2017_2_11","questionText":"11.  What phrase occurs three times to describe God’s action, and how does this repeated phrase change your thoughts about those who seem to get away with immorality and injustice?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 1:28-32.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:28-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_12","questionText":"12.  How is a “depraved” mind different from one that does “not think it worthwhile to retain knowledge of God”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_2_13","questionText":"13.  Share how God has changed your thinking about a sin of which you previously approved.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 1:18-32.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:18-32"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_2_14","questionText":"14.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_3?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_3","name":"Romans2017_3","memoryVerse":"“For since the creation of the world, God’s invisible qualities – his eternal power and divine nature – have been clearly seen, being understood from what has been made, so that people are without excuse.” – Romans 1:20 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_3_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 2:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_3","questionText":"3. Why are the people in this passage without excuse, and upon what does God base His judgment?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_4","questionText":"4. What does it mean to pass judgment, and how does this differ from knowing and teaching God’s standards? Tell how you struggle with passing judgment on others.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_5","questionText":"5. How has God showered you with kindness and patience, and how do you demonstrate these godly attributes toward others?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 2:5-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:5-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_6","questionText":"6. What do stubborn, unrepentant people store up for themselves, and what are you storing up? (See also Matthew 6:19-20; 12:35.)  ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"6:19-20"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"12:35"}]},{"id":"2017_3_7a","questionText":"7. a. From verses 7-11, list the results when people follow the path of good and when they follow the path of evil.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_7b","questionText":"7. b. What do your actions reveal about your heart attitude toward God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_8","questionText":"8. What standard will God use to judge people’s obedience?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 2:17-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:17-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_9a","questionText":"9. a. What privileges did God give the Jews, and what was their attitude toward their privileges?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_9b","questionText":"9. b.  What specific privileges has He given you, and how do you sometimes demonstrate the same attitude?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_10","questionText":"10. Which of the 10 Commandments did Paul accuse the Jews of breaking? List some common ways Christians who teach others about following Jesus fail to do what He says? (See Exodus 20:1-17; Matthew 7:21-23.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"20:1-17"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"7:21-23"}]},{"id":"2017_3_11","questionText":"11. What happens when any religious person violates the standards they proclaim? Is there an area of your life in which you may be guilty of this?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 2:25-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:25-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_3_12a","questionText":"12. a. What is circumcision, and why would this sign be a source of pride? (See Genesis 17:1-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:1-14"}]},{"id":"2017_3_12b","questionText":"12. b. Name some outward signs people today rely on to be in right relationship with God.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_3_13","questionText":"13. According to this passage, what is a true Jew, and what does this mean to you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 2.","questions":[{"id":"2017_3_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_4?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_4","name":"Romans2017_4","memoryVerse":"“For God does not show favoritism.” – Romans 2:11","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_4_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 3:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_3a","questionText":"3. a. What expectations might the Jews in Paul’s day have had about their spiritual advantages? (See also Romans 2:6-29.) What expectations of God do you have concerning any spiritual advantages you may have?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:6-29"}]},{"id":"2017_4_3b","questionText":"3. b. Why was it an advantage for the Jews that God entrusted them with His very words, and how is God’s Word, the Bible, a great advantage for you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_4","questionText":"4. Try to connect the promises God made to the Jews with Romans 3:3-4. (Some of the promises are found in Genesis 12:1-7; Deuteronomy 30:15-20; Jeremiah 31:35-37. There are several interpretations.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:3-4"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"12:1-7"},{"book":"Deuteronomy","verse":"30:15-20"},{"book":"Jeremiah","verse":"31:35-37"}]},{"id":"2017_4_5","questionText":"5. Ultimately, who is responsible for a person’s sin and unbelief? Why? (See Psalm 51:1-6; James 1:13-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"51:1-6"},{"book":"James","verse":"1:13-14"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 3:5-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:5-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_6","questionText":"6.  What “human argument” did Paul expose as wrong, and why was God’s wrath justified?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_7","questionText":"7. What should be the believer’s attitude toward sin, and how does your attitude toward sin compare with your  actions? (Use any Bible passages you wish to support your answer.) ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 3:9-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:9-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_8a","questionText":"8. a. From these verses, what are the promised effects of sin, and how have you seen these effects in your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_8b","questionText":"8. b. What words in verse 13-14 reveal how seriously God views our speech? What warning do you receive about your words, and what specifically will you ask God to help you change? (See also James 3:5-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"James","verse":"3:5-10"}]},{"id":"2017_4_9","questionText":"9. According to verse 18, what sin appears to underlie the sins in verses 13-17, and how does this passage show this root sin is true of people in both Old and New Testament times?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_10","questionText":"10.  What does it look like to fear (have a reverent awe for) God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 3:19-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:19-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_11","questionText":"11. What does Paul conclude in verses 19-20?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_12a","questionText":"12. a. What does it mean to have every mouth silenced and the whole world accountable to God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_4_12b","questionText":"12. b. How has the study of Romans helped you to identify, confess and repent of your sin?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 3:1-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:1-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_4_13","questionText":"13.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_5?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_5","name":"Romans2017_5","memoryVerse":"“As it is written: ‘There is no one righteous, not even one; there is no one who understands; there is no one who seeks God.’ ” – Romans 3:10-11","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_5_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 3:21-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:21-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_3","questionText":"3.  Define “righteousness.” Where does it come from, and how is it received? How does this compare with your  understanding of righteousness?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_4","questionText":"4.  What does “apart from the law” mean? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_5a","questionText":"5. a.  How does the Old Testament also show the righteousness God gives is apart from the law? Why does this matter? (See Genesis 15:6; Jeremiah 31:33-34; Ezekiel 36:26-27 or any other Old Testament reference.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:6"},{"book":"Jeremiah","verse":"31:33-34"},{"book":"Ezekiel","verse":"36:26-27"}]},{"id":"2017_5_5b","questionText":"5. b.  Who may receive God’s righteousness, and what is your response to His gift? (See also Romans 10:9-10, 14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:9-10"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:14"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 3:23-24.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:23-24"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_6","questionText":"6.  What examples might you use from the Bible, history, current culture or your own life to help an unbeliever under-stand “all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_7a","questionText":"7. a.  Define “justified.” How is justification accomplished, and why is that good news? (See also Genesis 15:6; Isaiah 53:11; 2 Corinthians 5:21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:6"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"53:11"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"5:21"}]},{"id":"2017_5_7b","questionText":"7. b.  Explain “the redemption that came by Christ Jesus”. What does redemption teach you about God? (For additional help see Mark 10:45; Ephesians 1:7-8; Titus 2:14; 1 Peter 1:18)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Mark","verse":"10:45"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:7-8"},{"book":"Titus","verse":"2:14"},{"book":"1 Peter","verse":"1:18"}]},{"id":"2017_5_8","questionText":"8.  How does God’s grace in justification and redemption reveal that you are loved and wanted by God? How does that impact your response to Him? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 3:24-26.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:24-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_9","questionText":"9.  What does it mean that Jesus is a  “sacrifice of atonement” (“propitiation,” ESV)? How does this assure you that God’s justice has been satisfied? (For help see Hebrews 2:17; 1 John 2:2; 4:10; use a dictionary if you wish.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"2:17"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"2:2"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"4:10"}]},{"id":"2017_5_10","questionText":"10.  Why would God present His own Son as a sacrifice of atonement and how can you express your gratitude for such great love?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 3:25-26.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:25-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_11","questionText":"11.  How did God demonstrate His righteousness in Jesus Christ? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_5_12","questionText":"12.  How can you know you will never have to face God’s just punishment and with whom will you share the freedom this knowledge gives?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 3:21-26.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:21-26"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_5_13","questionText":"13.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_6?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_6","name":"Romans2017_6","memoryVerse":"“This righteousness is given through faith in Jesus Christ to all who believe. There is no difference between Jew and Gentile, for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God.” – Romans 3:22-23 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_6_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 3:27-28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:27-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_3","questionText":"3. How do people today boast about their spirituality or relationship with God, and why is all boasting to be excluded?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_4","questionText":"4. Name some different ways people try to justify themselves before God. Which one most accurately applies to the way you live?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_5","questionText":"5. What is wrong with people’s hearts and relationships when they boast of their own righteousness, and how can you guard against self-righteousness?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 3:27-28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:27-28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_6","questionText":"6. List various ways people today understand and use the word “faith.” ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_7a","questionText":"7. a.  Read Hebrews 11. Describe in your own words the kind of faith that justifies or saves a person. (You may use any Scripture references to support your answer.) List some things these believers’ faith caused them to do.","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"11:1-40"}]},{"id":"2017_6_7b","questionText":"7. b. Share something your faith has recently prompted you to do.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 3:29-30.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:29-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_8","questionText":"8.  Who are Gentiles, and why would Jews in Paul’s day look down on them? (See Romans 2:17, 23, 25. Use a  dictionary if necessary.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:17"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:23"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:25"}]},{"id":"2017_6_9","questionText":"9. How does the fact that “there is only one God” and one way of salvation compare with how many people  think today?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_6_10","questionText":"10. What truths from this passage or previous lessons could you use to respond graciously to people who say all  religions are true or there are many gods or many ways to God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 3:31.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_11","questionText":"11.  How does faith uphold the law? (See Exodus 20:1-17; Romans 8:3-4; 13:8-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"20:1-17"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:3-4"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"13:8-10"}]},{"id":"2017_6_12","questionText":"12. Give examples of what goes wrong when people in the church believe they do not need to obey God’s commands and also teach others to disobey. (This thinking is called “antinomianism.”) (See also Jude 1:4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Jude","verse":"1:4"}]},{"id":"2017_6_13","questionText":"13.  If  God has justified you through faith, give examples of how He encourages and enables you to obey Him.  (See Romans 8:12-17, 31-34; Philippians 2:12-13; 1 John 1:5-10.)  ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:12-17"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:31-34"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"2:12-13"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"1:5-10"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 3:27-31.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:27-31"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_6_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_7?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_7","name":"Romans2017_7","memoryVerse":"“For we maintain that a person is justified by faith apart from the works of the law.” – Romans 3:28 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_7_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 4:1-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:1-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_3","questionText":"3. What did Abraham believe, and how did his life show his faith and honor God? (For additional help, see Genesis 12:1-9; 13:1-18; 15:1-6, 18; 17:1-10, 23.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"12:1-9"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"13:1-18"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:1-6"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:18"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:1-10"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:23"}]},{"id":"2017_7_4","questionText":"4. Why do workers not consider their wages a gift from their employers? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_5a","questionText":"5. a. What gift does God give all who trust Him, and what wages do people who insist on an employer-employee relationship with God earn? (See also Romans 6:23.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:23"}]},{"id":"2017_7_5b","questionText":"5. b. Which type of relationship with God do you have? What does your life reveal about your faith and expecta- tions of God?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 4:6-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:6-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_6","questionText":"6. How did David learn the truth he taught in Psalm 32, quoted in Romans 4:7-8? (See 2 Samuel 11-12; Psalm 32; 51.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Samuel","verse":"11:1-12:33"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"32:1-11"},{"book":"Psalm","verse":"51:1-19"}]},{"id":"2017_7_7","questionText":"7. How could these verses help believers who struggle with guilt from past sins? (You may use other verses from Scripture.) ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_8","questionText":"8. Privately and specifically, name sins God has counted against Christ instead of you. Share with your group a time you experienced the joy of forgiveness and how you will express thankfulness to Christ for taking your sin and giving you His righteousness. (See also 2 Corinthians 5:19-21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"5:19-21"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 4:9-15.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:9-15"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_9","questionText":"9. About how long after God declared Abraham righteous did He give the sign of circumcision to Abraham and the Law to Abraham’s descendants? Why is this sequence of events important? (See Genesis 15:6, 13-18; 16:1-4, 16; 17:25-26; Galatians 3:15-18.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:6"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"15:13-18"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"16:1-4"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"16:16"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"17:25-26"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"3:15-18"}]},{"id":"2017_7_10a","questionText":"10. a. What happens when people depend on their own obedience or on signs, such as circumcision, baptism or the Lord’s Supper, as a measure of their righteousness? What is the value of obedience and signs?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_10b","questionText":"10. b. Briefly explain why you believe you are or are not righteous in God’s eyes.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 4:16-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:16-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_11","questionText":"11. From these verses, describe the faith of Abraham and explain who Abraham’s offspring are.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_12","questionText":"12. How did Abraham face the facts of his situation, and what happened to his faith as he waited for God to fulfill  His promise? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_13","questionText":"13. What difficult situation has God used or is using to strengthen your faith?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:1-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_7_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_7_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 4","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_8?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_8","name":"Romans2017_8","memoryVerse":"“Yet he did not waver through unbelief regarding the promise of God, but was strengthened in his faith and gave glory to God, being fully persuaded that God had power to do what he had promised.” – Romans 4:20-21 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_8_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 5:1-2.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:1-2"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_3","questionText":"3. What does it mean to have peace with God, and how is it accomplished? How is this different from and superior to peaceful circumstances or feelings? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_4","questionText":"4. What access do believers have through Jesus Christ, and how should this privilege impact your daily life? (See also John 14:6; Ephesians 2:18; 3:12; Hebrews 4:14-16.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"14:6"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:18"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"3:12"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"4:14-16"}]},{"id":"2017_8_5","questionText":"5. Christians will see God’s glory in heaven. How might focusing on your “hope of the glory of God” strengthen you, comfort you or give you joy today? (See also Psalm 17:15; Matthew 5:8; 1 John 3:2; Revelation 22:3-4.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"17:15"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"5:8"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"3:2"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"22:3-4"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 5:3-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:3-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_6a","questionText":"6. a. Why and how can believers glory (rejoice or boast) in suffering?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_6b","questionText":"6. b.  How has God used your suffering to produce perseverance, character, hope and a deeper knowledge of His love in you and in those around you?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_7","questionText":"7. Why does hope not disappoint us or “put us to shame,” and what role does the Holy Spirit play in this process? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 5:6-8.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:6-8"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_8a","questionText":"8. a. Give three words from these verses that describe the condition of those for whom Christ died. Why is this good news?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_8b","questionText":"8. b. How do these three words make clear that people cannot save themselves, and what is your personal experience of this? (See also Ephesians 2:1-9.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-9"}]},{"id":"2017_8_9","questionText":"9. How might these verses help you explain why Christianity is unique as compared with other religions and  philosophies?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 5:9-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:9-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_10","questionText":"10. List various aspects of salvation from these verses.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_11a","questionText":"11. a.  Define “reconciliation.” (If needed, use a dictionary.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_11b","questionText":"11. b.  Is God reconciled to us or are we reconciled to God, and what does it reveal about God?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_12","questionText":"12. How are we saved through Christ’s life, and what words or actions will you use to boast (rejoice) in Him?  (See also Romans 4:25; 6:8-10; 8:34; or other Bible passages you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"4:25"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:8-10"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:34"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 5:1-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_8_13","questionText":"13. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_8_14","questionText":"14. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 5:1-11","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:1-11"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_9?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_9","name":"Romans2017_9","memoryVerse":"“Therefore, since we have been justified through faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ.” –  Romans 5:1","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_9_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 5:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_3","questionText":"3.  Read Genesis 2:15-3:24. Who was the “one man” in Romans 5:12? What warning did God give him, and what harm did his sin cause? (See also Romans 3:9-11, 23; 8:20-21; 1 Corinthians 15:22; Ephesians 2:1-3.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"2:15-3:24"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:9-11"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:23"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:20-21"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"15:22"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-3"}]},{"id":"2017_9_4","questionText":"4. What do most people you know believe about humanity – that all people are born good, born neutral or born  sinners? What do you believe and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 5:14-19.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:14-19"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_5","questionText":"5. List ways Adam (“a pattern”) and Jesus Christ (“the one to come”) are the same and ways they differ. How did Jesus bring more good than all that Adam destroyed? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_6","questionText":"6. What is the “gift”? Why do verses 15-17 mention it so often, and what is your response to it?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_7","questionText":"7. What unites people to Adam, and what unites them to Christ? To whom are you united, and how do you know? (See also John 3:7-21; Romans 10:9-13; or other Bible passages.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"3:7-21"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:9-13"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 5:18-19.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:18-19"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_8","questionText":"8. What are some results of condemnation, and what impact do these verses have on you? (See Matthew 13:47-50;  Romans 2:8-9; Philippians 3:18-19; 2 Thessalonians 1:8-9; Revelation 20:14-15.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"13:47-50"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:8-9"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:18-19"},{"book":"2 Thessalonians","verse":"1:8-9"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"20:14-15"}]},{"id":"2017_9_9a","questionText":"9. a. What is the “one righteous act” that resulted in justification and life? (Use other verses if you wish.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_9b","questionText":"9. b. What are some results of life in Christ, and how are they evident in your life? (See John 10:28; Galatians 2:20; Ephesians 3:12; Philippians 3:20-21; Hebrews 13:20-21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"10:28"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"2:20"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"3:12"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:20-21"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"13:20-21"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 5:20-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:20-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_10a","questionText":"10. a. Why does law cause trespass (sin) to increase? (See Romans 7:7-12; Galatians 3:24.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:7-12"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"3:24"}]},{"id":"2017_9_10b","questionText":"10. b. How do you see this principle at work in you, your family, community or country?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_11","questionText":"11. Share briefly a recent example of God’s grace overcoming the consequences of your sin.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_12","questionText":"12. What are the two reigns (kingdoms) in verse 21, and what happens to those who belong to each kingdom? (See also Colossians 1:13-14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Colossians","verse":"1:13-14"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 5:12-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_9_13","questionText":"13. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_9_14","questionText":"14. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 5:12-21","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-21"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_10?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_10","name":"Romans2017_10","memoryVerse":"“Consequently, just as one trespass resulted in condemnation for all people, so also one righteous act resulted in  justification and life for all people.” – Romans 5:18","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_10_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 6:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_3","questionText":"3. What thoughts in chapter 5 prompted Paul to ask the question in 6:1, and why? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_4","questionText":"4. What happens when Christians believe their sin does not matter? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_5","questionText":"5. When have you been tempted to sin because you knew God would forgive you? How might these verses strengthen you to fight sin instead?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 6:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_6","questionText":"6. Who are “we” and “us” in these verses?  If you are part of this group, rewrite verse 2 as your own statement. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_7","questionText":"7. Describe the spiritual reality to which water baptism points. (See also Acts 1:5; 2:38; 1 Corinthians 12:13;  Galatians 3:26-27; Colossians 2:11-12.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"1:5"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"2:38"},{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"12:13"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"3:26-27"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"2:11-12"}]},{"id":"2017_10_8","questionText":"8.  Specifically how does Paul say believers have died to sin?  If Christ is your Savior, how have you experienced this death personally and how are you now living a new life? (See also Romans 5:12-21; 2 Corinthians 5:14-21.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:12-21"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"5:14-21"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 6:5-10.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:5-10"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_9","questionText":"9. From these verses, name ways believers are united with Christ.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_10","questionText":"10. What does Paul mean by “the old self ”? (See also Ephesians 4:22-24; Colossians 3:9-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:22-24"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:9-10"}]},{"id":"2017_10_11","questionText":"11. For which aspects of your union with Christ will you thank God, and where do you need His help to believe He has set you free from sin? (See also Colossians 2:11-15.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Colossians","verse":"2:11-15"}]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 6:9-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:9-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_12","questionText":"12. List facts about Jesus from verses 9-10. How does verse 11 connect your life with what is true of Jesus?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_13","questionText":"13. What does it look like to be dead to sin but alive to Christ: In your home? In your school, workplace or community? In your church?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 6:1-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_10_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_10_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 6:1-11","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-11"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_11?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_11","name":"Romans2017_11","memoryVerse":"“In the same way, count yourselves dead to sin but alive to God in Christ Jesus.” – Romans 6:11 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_11_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 6:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_3","questionText":"3. What truths in earlier chapters of Romans precede the word “therefore” in verse 12? (See previous lessons.)  ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_4a","questionText":"4. a. List the two negative commands and the two positive commands, and explain why lasting change requires both negative and positive actions. (See also Ephesians 4:22-24; Colossians 3:9-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:22-24"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:9-10"}]},{"id":"2017_11_4b","questionText":"4. b.  Give specific ways you are tempted to offer any part of yourself to sin and ways to offer every part of yourself to God.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_5","questionText":"5. How does God’s promise in verse 14 encourage you in light of the commands in verses 12-13? (See also Romans 5:20-21.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:20-21"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 6:15-16.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:15-16"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_6","questionText":"6. How do the questions in verses 1 and 15 differ, and how are they alike?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_7a","questionText":"7. a. What does it mean to “be a slave to sin” or a “slave to righteousness”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_7b","questionText":"7. b. Because we are slaves to the one we obey, would you describe yourself now as a slave to sin or a slave to righteousness, and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 6:17-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:17-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_8","questionText":"8. Compare and contrast obedience from the heart and following rules. Which describes your actions?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_9","questionText":"9. What is “the pattern of teaching” Paul says “claims the allegiance” of believers? (See Romans 6:1-14 or other Scripture passages.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-14"}]},{"id":"2017_11_10","questionText":"10. If Christ has set you free from sin, what are some aspects of your freedom for which you thank God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 6:19-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:19-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_11","questionText":"11. List ways in which people want to be free and why these things are or are not true freedom.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_12","questionText":"12. What are the results of being a slave to sin, and what are the results of being a slave to God? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_13a","questionText":"13. a. How have you personally experienced sin’s wages, which lead to death? If you are a believer, how has God used those things for His glory and your good?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_13b","questionText":"13. b. What attitudes and behaviors are produced in you as you meditate on God’s gift of eternal life?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 6:12-23.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:12-23"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_11_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_11_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 6:12-23","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:12-23"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_12?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_12","name":"Romans2017_12","memoryVerse":"“For the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.” – Romans 6:23 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_12_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 7:1-6.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:1-6"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_3","questionText":"3. How do these verses build on the truth of the believer’s union with Christ? (See Romans 6:1-11, 14.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:1-11"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"6:14"}]},{"id":"2017_12_4a","questionText":"4. a. From what does Christ’s death free believers, to whom do they now belong and what is their purpose?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_4b","questionText":"4. b. If you are a believer, how are you living out your God-given purpose and freedom, especially in your relation- ships in work, family, community life, etc.?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_5","questionText":"5. Contrast “fruit for God” and “the new way of the Spirit” with “fruit for death” and “the old way of the written code.” (See also John 15:1-5 and Galatians 5:16-23.) Where do you see these patterns in your life? ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"15:1-5"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:16-23"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 7:7-13. Note: Christians differ about whether Romans 7:7-25 refers to Paul’s life before or after Jesus saved him.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:7-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_6","questionText":"6. From verses 7-13, what does the law do for people, and how does sin use the law against people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_7","questionText":"7. How does sin deceive you and harm your mind, emotions or body? What does sin reveal about your understanding of God and how will you respond to what He is showing you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 7:14-20.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:14-20"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_8","questionText":"8. Explain how the law is “spiritual” and why Paul describes himself as “unspiritual.”","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_9","questionText":"9. How would you explain Paul’s struggle in these verses to your family or others you want to help grow in Christ?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_10","questionText":"10. What do you do that you do not want to do, and what good do you not do that you really want to do?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 7:21-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:21-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_11","questionText":"11. Describe Paul’s distress over sin in these verses. ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_12a","questionText":"12. a. How does Paul answer the question he asked in verse 24?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_12b","questionText":"12. b. Why is Paul’s answer the only true help for those who live under the burden of the law as well as those who tend to lawless living?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_13","questionText":"13. Can you share a time distress over sin led you to desperate prayer, and how might Romans 6 and 7 help you pray about your ongoing struggle with sin?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 7:1-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"7:1-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_12_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_12_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 7","answer":"","quotes":[]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_13?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_13","name":"Romans2017_13","memoryVerse":"“What a wretched man I am! Who will rescue me from this body that is subject to death? Thanks be to God, who  delivers me through Jesus Christ our Lord!” – Romans 7:24-25a","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_13_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 8:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_3a","questionText":"3. a.  From your study of Romans 1-7, how would you explain Romans 8:1? What is the significance of “now” and “no condemnation”? (For additional help, see John 3:16-17; 5:24.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1"},{"book":"John","verse":"3:16-17"},{"book":"John","verse":"5:24"}]},{"id":"2017_13_3b","questionText":"3. b. How does Romans 8:1 affect the way you view yourself and others? What changes will you ask God to make in your thoughts or actions?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1"}]},{"id":"2017_13_4","questionText":"4.  How does this passage show that the whole Trinity (Father, Son and Holy Spirit) works to save sinners? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_5","questionText":"5.  Because those in Christ are no longer under law, why and how do they fulfill the law’s righteous requirements?  (See also John 14:15-21; 16:5-15.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"14:15-21"},{"book":"John","verse":"16:5-15"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 8:5-11.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:5-11"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_6","questionText":"6.  Name the two basic groups of people these verses describe and contrast their mindsets and lives.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_7","questionText":"7.  How can you recognize a mind set on what the Spirit desires? (See also Galatians 5:22-23; Colossians 3:1-4.) Would others say that is true of you? ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:22-23"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:1-4"}]},{"id":"2017_13_8","questionText":"8.  According to verses 9-11, what things are true of everyone in whom the Spirit of God (also called the Spirit of Christ) lives, and how do these truths encourage you today?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 8:12-14.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:12-14"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_9","questionText":"9.  According to these verses, what is a Christian’s obligation and why? (See also 2 Corinthians 7:1; Philippians  3:10-14; 1 John 3:1-3.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"7:1"},{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:10-14"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"3:1-3"}]},{"id":"2017_13_10a","questionText":"10. a.  How can God’s children “put to death the misdeeds of the body”? (See also Galatians 5:13-26; Colossians 3:5-17.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Galatians","verse":"5:13-26"},{"book":"Colossians","verse":"3:5-17"}]},{"id":"2017_13_10b","questionText":"10. b.  What does the phrase “put to death” teach about the attitude God’s children are to have toward their sin, and where do you need the Holy Spirit’s help to change your attitude and actions?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 8:14-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:14-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_11","questionText":"11.  List privileges of adoption into God’s family. (See also Romans 8:29.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29"}]},{"id":"2017_13_12","questionText":"12.   From the following verses, give additional benefits of being God’s child and, if you are a believer, express how you have experienced these benefits.  (Matthew 6:7-8; 10:29-31; Hebrews 12:7-11; 1 John 3:1-3) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"6:7-8"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"10:29-31"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"12:7-11"},{"book":"1 John","verse":"3:1-3"}]},{"id":"2017_13_13","questionText":"13.  How might these truths help you or others who struggle with doubt of God’s fatherly love?    ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 8:1-17.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1-17"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_13_14","questionText":"14.  What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_13_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 8:1-17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1-17"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_14?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_14","name":"Romans2017_14","memoryVerse":"“Therefore, there is now no condemnation for those who are in Christ Jesus.” – Romans 8:1","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_14_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 8:17-18.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:17-18"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_3","questionText":"3. What was Paul’s experience with suffering, and how does this affect your understanding of these verses and encourage you in your suffering?  (See 2 Corinthians 4:7-18; 6:4-10; 11:23-28 or other verses you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"4:7-18"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"6:4-10"},{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"11:23-28"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4a","questionText":"4. a. What does the word “glory” mean? (Use a dictionary for help.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_4b","questionText":"4. b. Give various aspects of our “glory” from the following verses:  2 Corinthians 3:18","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Corinthians","verse":"3:18"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4c","questionText":"4. b.  Philippians 3:20-21","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Philippians","verse":"3:20-21"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4d","questionText":"4. b.  Colossians 1:27","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Colossians","verse":"1:27"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4e","questionText":"4. b.  2 Thessalonians 2:13-14","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Thessalonians","verse":"2:13-14"}]},{"id":"2017_14_4f","questionText":"4. b.  Hebrews 2:10","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"2:10"}]},{"id":"2017_14_5","questionText":"5. What is the relationship between suffering and glory, and what hope does this give you for yourself, your church or for suffering believers worldwide?  (See references given above or other verses you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 8:19-22.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:19-22"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_6","questionText":"6. What does Paul mean by “creation” in this passage?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_7","questionText":"7. List ways you see the creation subject to frustration and decay today. (See also Genesis 1:27-2:1; 3:17-19.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Genesis","verse":"1:27-2:1"},{"book":"Genesis","verse":"3:17-19"}]},{"id":"2017_14_8","questionText":"  8. When and how will creation be liberated? (See 2 Peter 3:13; Revelation 21:1 or other verses you may know.) How do these truths help you distinguish proper creation care from idolizing nature or trusting in people’s efforts to renew the planet?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"2 Peter","verse":"3:13"},{"book":"Revelation","verse":"21:1"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 8:23-25.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:23-25"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_9","questionText":"  9. Who and what groan in these verses, and why do they groan? (See also Romans 8:22, 26.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:22"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:26"}]},{"id":"2017_14_10a","questionText":"10. a. For what do Christians hope, and how are they to wait?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_10b","questionText":"10. b. For what are you waiting and hoping, and why?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 8:26-27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:26-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_11","questionText":"11. From these verses, share various ways the Holy Spirit works in a believer’s life and at least one way He has been working in yours. Romans 8:26-27","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:26-27"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11b","questionText":"11. Luke 12:12","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Luke","verse":"12:12"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11c","questionText":"11. Acts 1:8","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"1:8"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11d","questionText":"11. Acts 16:6-10; 20:22","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Acts","verse":"16:6-10"},{"book":"Acts","verse":"20:22"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11e","questionText":"11. Ephesians 4:3-4","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"4:3-4"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11f","questionText":"11. Ephesians 6:17","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"6:17"}]},{"id":"2017_14_11g","questionText":"11. 1 Corinthians 2:12","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"1 Corinthians","verse":"2:12"}]},{"id":"2017_14_12a","questionText":"12. a. What is meant by “the Spirit intercedes for God’s people in accordance with the will of God”?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_12b","questionText":"12. b. Who, besides the Holy Spirit, intercedes for you today, and for whom do you pray? (See Romans 8:34 or  other verses you may know.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:34"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 8:18-27.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:18-27"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_14_13","questionText":"13. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_14_14","questionText":"14. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 8:18-27","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:18-27"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_15?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_15","name":"Romans2017_15","memoryVerse":"“I consider that our present sufferings are not worth comparing with the glory that will be revealed in us.” – Romans 8:18 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_15_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 8:28.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_3","questionText":"3. What is the “good” that God works for His people in all things? (See also Romans 8:29-39.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29-39"}]},{"id":"2017_15_4a","questionText":"4. a. Put Romans 8:28 in your own words. What assurances does this verse offer the believer in every situation?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28"}]},{"id":"2017_15_4b","questionText":"4. b. How might you pray when struggling with things that you wonder how God will use for good?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_5","questionText":"5. What do you learn about God’s attributes and character from Romans 8:28, and how does this challenge or comfort you?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28"}]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 8:29-30.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29-30"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_6","questionText":"6.  a.  Briefly explain the following concepts. (For help, see John 6:37, 44; Romans 1:6-7; 3:22-26; 8:17-21;  Ephesians 1:4-5, 11 or other Bible passages.)  Foreknew","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"John","verse":"6:37"},{"book":"John","verse":"6:44"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:6-7"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"3:22-26"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:17-21"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:4-5"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:11"}]},{"id":"2017_15_6b","questionText":"6.  a.  Predestined","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6c","questionText":"6.  a.  Called","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6d","questionText":"6.  a.   Justified","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6e","questionText":"6.  a.   Glorified","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_6f","questionText":"6. b. What does Romans 8:29-30 reveal about God, and why is it good news?","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:29-30"}]},{"id":"2017_15_7","questionText":"7.  What are some ways God works to conform believers to the image of His Son? What are some reasons many professing believers do not act like Jesus? (See also Romans 5:3-5; 2 Timothy 3:12, 15-16; Hebrews 5:7-8 or other Bible passages.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"5:3-5"},{"book":"2 Timothy","verse":"3:12"},{"book":"2 Timothy","verse":"3:15-16"},{"book":"Hebrews","verse":"5:7-8"}]},{"id":"2017_15_8","questionText":"  8. How do you see God at work in your life to make you more Christlike?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 8:31-35.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:31-35"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_9","questionText":"  9. List the questions and answers in verses 31-35. What conclusions can you draw based on these questions and answers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_10","questionText":"10. With which of the previous questions are you struggling, and how do the answers encourage you?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 8:35-39.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:35-39"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_11","questionText":"11.  Why does Paul quote Psalm 44:22 to answer the questions verse 35 asks? (See also John 16:33.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Psalm","verse":"44:22"},{"book":"John","verse":"16:33"}]},{"id":"2017_15_12","questionText":"12.  a.  How do “all these things” in verses 35-37 relate to “all things” in verses 28 and 32?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_12b","questionText":"12. b.  How has a deeper understanding of Christ’s love helped you in a specific difficulty this year?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_13","questionText":"13. List things in your life or world events that tempt you to worry or prompt anger and impatience. Use your list to rewrite verses 38-39 as your own statement of confidence in God’s love for you.","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 8:28-39.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28-39"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_15_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_15_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 8:28-39","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:28-39"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_16?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_16","name":"Romans2017_16","memoryVerse":"“He who did not spare his own Son, but gave him up for us all — how will he not also, along with him, graciously give us all things?” – Romans 8:32","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes and the references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_16_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 9:1-5.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-5"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_3","questionText":"3.  What truth does Paul affirm? Why is Paul grieving for the people of Israel and how is he like Moses and Jesus? (For additional help see Exodus 32:30-32; Luke 19:41-44; John 10:11; Romans 9:1-29.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"32:30-32"},{"book":"Luke","verse":"19:41-44"},{"book":"John","verse":"10:11"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-29"}]},{"id":"2017_16_4a","questionText":"4. a. Explain what “cursed” means in Romans 9:3 and whether any believer might ever be “cut off” from Christ. What do you think is Paul’s point? (See also Romans 8:1, 35, 38-39.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:3"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:1"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:35"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"8:38-39"}]},{"id":"2017_16_4b","questionText":"4. b. How does Paul’s love for the unbelieving people of Israel model the way believers should respond to unbelievers?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_5","questionText":"5. Consider the spiritual advantages God has given you. What are their benefits? How are they sometimes squandered? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 9:6-13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:6-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_6a","questionText":"6. a. How is God true to His Word despite the unbelief of the majority of the Israelite people?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_6b","questionText":"6. b. What examples does Paul give to prove that physical birth never automatically makes anyone God’s child? (See also Romans 2:28-29.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"2:28-29"}]},{"id":"2017_16_7","questionText":"7. How do these verses show salvation is by grace and not human effort? What hope does this give you for your unbelieving family members, friends or co-workers?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 9:14-21.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:14-21"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_8","questionText":"8. What does Paul’s use of Bible history reveal about God and how He elects to work out His righteous and holy will? How does this compare with your understanding?  (See also Exodus 7:3, 13; 8:32; 14:4.) ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Exodus","verse":"7:3"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"7:13"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"8:32"},{"book":"Exodus","verse":"14:4"}]},{"id":"2017_16_9a","questionText":"9. a. From verses 20-21, explain in your own words the problem with people accusing God of injustice. (See also Isaiah 29:16; 64:8; Jeremiah 18:6; 2 Timothy 2:20.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"29:16"},{"book":"Isaiah","verse":"64:8"},{"book":"Jeremiah","verse":"18:6"},{"book":"2 Timothy","verse":"2:20"}]},{"id":"2017_16_9b","questionText":"9. b. Give examples of how people today (perhaps even you) use similar reasons to excuse sin or accuse God of injustice.","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_10","questionText":"10. How has God shown you mercy when your heart was hard, and how have you responded to Him? ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 9:22-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:22-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_11","questionText":"11. In verses 22-24, how and why does God demonstrate His power and mercy?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_12","questionText":"12.  What about the riches of God’s glory move you to prayer, praise or practical actions? (See also Ephesians 1:7-8, 18-23; 2:1-10.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:7-8"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"1:18-23"},{"book":"Ephesians","verse":"2:1-10"}]},{"id":"2017_16_13","questionText":"13. What do you learn about God’s mercy and grace to Jews and Gentiles from the Hosea and Isaiah quotations?  (See also Romans 11:3-6.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"11:3-6"}]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 9:1-29.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-29"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_16_14","questionText":"14. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_16_15","questionText":"15. Homiletics for group and administrative leaders: Romans 9:1-29","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:1-29"}]}]}}},"LESSON/2017_17?lang=eng":{"id":"2017_17","name":"Romans2017_17","memoryVerse":"“What if he did this to make the riches of his glory known to the objects of his mercy, whom he prepared in advance for glory – even us, whom he also called, not only from the Jews but also from the Gentiles?” – Romans 9:23-24 ","dayQuestions":{"one":{"title":"FIRST DAY: Read the notes with references.","questions":[{"id":"2017_17_1","questionText":"1. What was meaningful to you in the lecture?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_2","questionText":"2. What help did you receive from the notes?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"two":{"title":"SECOND DAY: Read Romans 9:30-33.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:30-33"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_3","questionText":"3. What was the difference in the way the Gentiles and Israel approached righteousness? What were the results?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_4","questionText":"4. How is daily pursuing righteous behavior different from striving for righteous standing? What role does faith play?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_5","questionText":"5. Who is “the stumbling stone”? What about “the stumbling stone” causes people to stumble or fall?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"three":{"title":"THIRD DAY: Read Romans 10:1-4.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:1-4"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_6","questionText":"6. Why would Paul so strongly desire the Israelites be saved? How has God called you to pray for and minister tothose you desire to be saved?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_7","questionText":"7. What knowledge did the Israelites lack that caused their zeal to be misdirected? What does zealous behaviorwithout true knowledge of Jesus look like in today’s world? (Focus on behaviors without naming groups.)","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_8","questionText":"8. Explain Romans 10:4 in your own words. (You may want to read additional Bible translations to help you.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:4"}]}]},"four":{"title":"FOURTH DAY: Read Romans 10:5-9.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:5-9"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_9","questionText":"9. What conclusions does Paul make in light of these verses? (Note: Romans 10:5-7 can be interpreted in  various ways.)","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:5-7"}]},{"id":"2017_17_10","questionText":"10. What must a person do to be saved? ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_11","questionText":"11. How would you take each phrase of verse 9 and explain its meaning and importance to an unbeliever?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"five":{"title":"FIFTH DAY: Read Romans 10:10-13","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"10:10-13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_12","questionText":"12. Share different aspects of the word “heart” from the following references: Matthew 6:21; 12:34; Romans 1:21-22; Galatians 4:6. As you meditate on these verses, what is God showing you about your heart? ","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Matthew","verse":"6:21"},{"book":"Matthew","verse":"12:34"},{"book":"Romans","verse":"1:21-22"},{"book":"Galatians","verse":"4:6"}]},{"id":"2017_17_13","questionText":"13. How does verse 13 relate to and clarify verse 11? According to these verses, to whom is salvation available?  ","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_14","questionText":"14. When did you (or will you) call on the name of the Lord for salvation?","answer":"","quotes":[]}]},"six":{"title":"SIXTH DAY: Review Romans 9:30-10:13.","readVerse":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:30-10:13"}],"questions":[{"id":"2017_17_15","questionText":"15. What have you learned about God in this week’s study? How may your group pray for you as you make this truth a part of your life?","answer":"","quotes":[]},{"id":"2017_17_16","questionText":"16. Homiletics for discussion and administrative leaders: Romans 9:30-10:13","answer":"","quotes":[{"book":"Romans","verse":"9:30-10:13"}]}]}}}}